Guide to the James Watson Webb Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James Watson Webb papers
1819-1890
MS 683
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
21.75
The James Watson Webb papers consist of correspondence, letterbooks, newspapers, diaries, and miscellanea documenting the personal life and professional career of James Watson Webb and his family, including his second wife, Laura Virginia Cram Webb. The papers document Webb's journalistic and political careers, his personal life, and the activities and observations of his second wife, Laura Virginia Cram Webb, a close confidante to her husband. Major topics of interest include New York politics and life, national politics, the Civil War, foreign relations with France and Brazil, and the social life of New York and Washington, D.C. As a major New York City newspaper publisher and a U.S. diplomat to Brazil, Webb corresponded with such figures as Nicholas Biddle, James Blaine, Lewis Cass, Henry Clay, Hamilton Fish, Abraham Lincoln, William Marcy, Napoleon III, William Seward and others.
Webb, J. Watson (James Watson), 1802-1884
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were given to Yale University Library by Mrs. William Seward Webb, Col. G. Creighton Webb, F. Edgerton Webb, and the children of Alexander Stewart Webb in 1936. The papers were originally given as the Webb Papers. They have been divided into three collections: the Samuel Blachley Webb Papers, the Alexander Stewart Webb Papers, and the James Watson Webb Papers. Additional James Watson Webb papers were transferred from the Syracuse University Library in 1992 and Shelburne Farms in 2001.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and two additions: I. Correspondence and Papers, 1819-1888. II. Letterbooks, Papers, Newspapers and Miscellanea, 1827-1889. III. Laura Virginia Cram Webb Diaries and Papers, 1849-1890.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, letterbooks, diaries, newspapers, and miscellanea documenting the personal life and professional career of James Watson Webb (1802-1884) and his family, including his second, wife Laura Virginia Cram Webb. The papers document Webb's journalistic and political careers, his personal life, and the activities and observations of his second wife, who was a close confidante to her husband. Major topics of interest include New York politics and life, national politics, the Civil War, foreign relations with France and Brazil, and the social life of New York and Washington, D.C. As a major New York City newspaper publisher and a U.S. diplomat to Brazil, Webb corresponded with such figures as: James Blaine, Lewis Cass, Henry Clay, Hamilton Fish, Abraham Lincoln, William Marcy, Napoleon, III, William Seward, and others.
The James Watson Webb Papers are organized in forty-three (43) boxes and total twenty-one (21) linear feet. The papers are arranged in the following series: I. Correspondence and Papers, 1819-1888; II. Letterbooks, Papers, Newspapers and Miscellanea, 1827-1889; and III. Laura Virginia Cram Webb Diaries and Papers, 1849-1890.
SERIES I, CORRESPONDENCE AND PAPERS, 1819-1888, contains the personal and professional letters of James Watson Webb. Chronological files include a small amount of material relating to Webb's early life as a soldier in Illinois and Michigan. The bulk of correspondence focuses on Webb's journalistic career as a newspaper editor in New York and as a United States diplomat. Webb's newspaper activities reflected his personal views and political motivations, and he worked to make the New York Courier the largest circulating paper in the country. In the era of Jacksonian politics Webb corresponded with such figures as Nicholas Biddle, James Gordon Bennett, James G. Blaine, Lewis Cass, Henry Clay, Edward Everett, Hamilton Fish, A mos Kendall, William Marcy, Mordecai Ma. (M.M.) Noah, William Seward, Thurlow Weed, Daniel Webster and many others.
In his transition from Jacksonian Democrat to Whig Party member, Webb seldom failed to touch upon a major political issue or individual in his correspondence and writings. His newspaper battles occasionally resulted in a resort to the gentleman's "code of honor," or a duel. One such instance involved Webb and Congressman Thomas F. Marshall of Kentucky. The resulting arrest, trial, and conviction of Webb in 1842 generated a great deal of support for him. Correspondence with Governor William Seward, a friend who advised Webb on how to obtain a pardon, and a letterbook containing numerous notes of support (SERIES II, box 32, folder 263) document this incident.
A verbal duel with the novelist James Fenimore Cooper, which culminated in a series of libel suits against Webb and the Courier, is also documented. Transcripts of court testimony and other material from 1833-1843 are included in this section. Correspondence relating to Webb's ill-fated appointment as charge d'affaires to Austria (1850) and his later appointment as minister to Brazil (1861) detail his political career (see also: SERIES II, boxes 33-35).
Select files contain a small quantity of personal correspondence, primarily from Webb's children, although letters from Daniel Webster are also organized in this section.
SERIES II, LETTERBOOKS, PAPERS, NEWSPAPERS, AND MISCELLANEA, 1827-1889, contains correspondence, in the form of letterbooks and letterpress copy-books, and other papers, including selected issues of newspapers which Webb published or retained for informational purposes. A small quantity of pictorial material is also included in this series.
Letterbooks includes a volume of letters relating to Webb's conviction and pardon for dueling (1842). Letterpress Copybooks contains two volumes relating to Webb's diplomatic duties, including letters from Napoleon, III.
SERIES III, LAURA VIRGINIA CRAM WEBB DIARIES AND PAPERS, 1849-1890, contains several volumes of a personal diary maintained by Webb's second wife from 1849-1890. The entries provide a vague if somewhat routine account of the daily lives of the Webbs. Additional material includes a volume documenting the work of many household servants employed by the Webb family.
Biographical / Historical
James Watson Webb was born in Claverack, New York on February 8, 1802. Webb's military career included service in Illinois during the 1820s. In 1827 his journalistic career began with the acquisition of the New York Morning Courier. In 1829 he acquired and merged the New York Enquirer with the Courier. In 1861 he sold his newspaper interest to the New York World. Webb was a nationally prominent journalist and editor whose writings sometimes resulted in libel suits and duels. During the Civil War he held the diplomatic post of Minister to Brazil, in support of the Union cause. He married twice, in 1823, and in 1849, to Laura Virginia Cram. He died on June 7, 1884.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Armed Forces; Journalism; Newspapers; Brazil; France; Latin America; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); United States -- Foreign relations; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- Politics and government; Women; Diaries; Editors; Journalists; Napoleon, Emperor of the French, III, 1808-1873; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848; Barnum, P. T. (Phineas Taylor), 1810-1891; Bennett, James Gordon, 1795-1872; Biddle, Nicholas, 1786-1844; Blaine, James Gillespie, 1830-1893; Buchanan, James, 1791-1868; Byron, George Anson Byron, Baron, 1789-1868; Cameron, Simon, 1799-1889; Cass, Lewis, 1782-1866; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852; Cooper, James Fenimore, 1789-1851; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865; Fillmore, Millard, 1800-1874; Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893; Frémont, John Charles, 1813-1890; Hamlin, Hannibal, 1809-1891; Hull, Isaac, 1773-1843; Irving, Washington, 1783-1859; Johnson, Reverdy, 1796-1876; Kendall, Amos, 1789-1869; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Macaulay, Thomas Babington Macaulay, Baron, 1800-1859; Mangum, Willie Person, 1792-1861; Marcy, William L. (William Learned), 1786-1857; Noah, M. M. (Mordecai Manuel), 1785-1851; Payne, John Howard, 1791-1852; Ponsonby, Richard Ponsonby, 1807-1866; Raymond, Henry J. (Henry Jarvis), 1820-1869; Scott, Winfield, 1786-1866; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872; Taylor, Zachary, 1784-1850; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852; Weed, Thurlow, 1797-1882
- CORRESPONDENCE AND PAPERS, 1819-1888; Series I; 130' (31 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is divided into two sections: Chronological and Select.
  - Chronological
    - 1819-1841 January (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
      General
      See also: box 37, folder 305
    - 1841 February-1843 March (Box 2, Folder 15-30)
    - 1843 April-1845 June (Box 3, Folder 31-44)
    - 1845 July-1850 June (Box 4, Folder 45-60)
    - 1850 July-1856 (Box 5, Folder 61-74)
    - 1857-1861 July (Box 6, Folder 75-87)
    - 1861 August-1862 July (Box 7, Folder 88-96)
    - 1862 April-July (Box 8, Folder 97-103)
    - 1862 August-November (Box 9, Folder 104-110)
    - 1862 December-1863 May 22 (Box 10, Folder 111-117)
    - 1863 May 23-August (Box 11, Folder 118-125)
    - 1863 September-December (Box 12, Folder 126-131)
    - 1863: Steamship concession (Box 12, Folder 132)
    - 1864 January-July (Box 13, Folder 133-140)
    - 1864 August-December (Box 14, Folder 141-147)
    - 1865 January-June (Box 15, Folder 148-154)
    - 1865 July-1866 July (Box 16, Folder 155-160)
    - 1866 August-1867 April (Box 17, Folder 161-167)
    - 1867 May-September (Box 18, Folder 168-174)
    - 1867 October-1868 April (Box 19, Folder 175-181)
    - 1868 May-September 25 (Box 20, Folder 182-187)
    - 1868 September 26-1869 April (Box 21, Folder 188-195)
    - 1869 May-1870 July (Box 22, Folder 196-201)
    - 1870 August-1871 (Box 23, Folder 202-207)
    - 1872-1873 June (Box 24, Folder 208-214)
    - 1873 July-1875 April (Box 25, Folder 215-220)
    - 1875 May-1877 (Box 26, Folder 221-227)
    - 1878-1884 June (Box 27, Folder 228-234)
    - 1884 July-1888 (Box 28, Folder 235-241)
  - Select
    - A-L, undated (Box 29, Folder 242-248)
    - M-Webb, Frank, undated (Box 30, Folder 249-253)
    - Webb, George Creighton, undated (Box 30, Folder 254)
    - Webb, Helen L., undated (Box 30, Folder 254)
    - Webb, Henry Watter, undated (Box 30, Folder 255)
    - Webb, Jacob Louis, undated (Box 31, Folder 256)
    - Webb, James Watson (correspondence with children), undated (Box 31, Folder 257)
    - Webb, Kate, undated (Box 31, Folder 258)
    - Webb, Laura Virinia, undated (Box 31, Folder 258)
    - Webb, Leila-Webb, Lilly, undated (Box 31, Folder 259)
    - Webb, Louise-Webb, Stephen, undated (Box 31, Folder 260)
    - Webb, William Seward, undated (Box 31, Folder 261)
    - Webster, Daniel-Y, unidentified, undated (Box 31, Folder 262)
- LETTERBOOKS, PAPERS, NEWSPAPERS, AND MISCELLANEA, 1827-1889; Series II; 6.0' (6 boxes)
  This series is divided into four sections: Letterbooks, Papers, Newspapers, and Miscellanea.
  - Letterbooks
    - 1842 September 12-November 26 (Box 32, Folder 263)
    - 1859-1870 (Box 33, Folder 264)
  - Letterpress copybooks
    - 1862 January 6-1868 October 15 (Box 33, Folder 265)
    - 1861 October 5-1865 July 12 (Box 34, Folder 266)
  - Papers
    - Account books, 1856-1874 (Box 35, Folder 267-269)
    - Calling cards, invitations, undated (Box 35, Folder 270)
    - Maps, undated (Box 35, Folder 271)
    - Notebook: family genealogy, undated (Box 35, Folder 272)
    - Papers, undated (Box 35, Folder 273-275)
    - Papers, undated (Box 36, Folder 276-278)
    - Printed material
      - Biographical data, 1858 (Box 36, Folder 279)
      - Facts for the People, 1853-1854 (Box 36, Folder 280)
      - Miscellanea, 1869, 1871, undated (Box 36, Folder 281)
      - Facts for the People, 1834-1869 (Box 36, Folder 282-285)
  - Newspapers
    - General, 1827-1885 (Box 37, Folder 286-296)
    - Miscellanea, 1852-1889 (Box 37, Folder 297)
    - Select
      - Biographical sketches, 1873, 1882 (Box 37, Folder 298)
      - Brazil, 1869 (Box 37, Folder 299)
      - Civil War, 1861 (Box 37, Folder 300)
      - Cuba, 1869-1873 (Box 37, Folder 301)
      - New York Morning Courier-Enquirer, 1853-1854 (Box 37, Folder 302-303)
      - New York Tribune, 1863-1880 (Box 37, Folder 304)
  - Miscellanea
    - Correspondence and papers: oversize, 1839-1840,1863, 1866 (Box 37, Folder 305)
    - Photographs, pictorial material, embroidery, undated (Box 37, Folder 306)
- LAURA VIRGINIA WEBB DIARIES AND PAPERS, 1849-1890; Series III; 2 linear feet (6 boxes)
  This series is divided into two sections: Diaries and Papers
  - Diaries
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Many of the diaries are missing pages or portions of pages. It is unknown who removed the material. The varying methods suggest that more than one person may have been responsible and that it was done prior to receipt by the repository.
    - 1849-1859 (Box 38, Folder 307-314)
    - 1860-1868 September (Box 39, Folder 315-321)
    - 1868 October-1875 May (Box 40, Folder 322-331)
    - 1875 June-1882 (Box 41, Folder 332-339)
    - 1884-1890 (Box 42, Folder 340-346)
  - Papers
    - Dictionary: Portuguese, 1860 (Box 42, Folder 347)
    - Notebooks
      - Domestic employees, 1851-1858 (Box 43, Folder 348)
      - Washington, D.C., 1855-1857 (Box 43, Folder 349)
      - Inventory, 1857-1870 (Box 43, Folder 350)
    - Miscellanea, 1859-1889, undated (Box 43, Folder 351)
- Additional Material, Accession 1992-M-083
  This addition is comprised of correspondence, arranged in two sections: incoming and outgoing. Each section is arranged alphabetically by author. The majority of the letters concern James Watson Webb's views on state and national politics, business affairs, social relations, and his attempts to be appointed Postmaster of New York City in 1841. A few letters relate to personal matters such as his wife's death and the baptism of his child. The letters range in date from the 1820s to the 1850s.
  - Correspondence, incoming
    - A-G (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - H-Z (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, outgoing (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-018
  - Ledger containing records of provisions for the United States Army kept by Lieutenants Benjamin Walker and James Watson Webb, ca. 1823-1835 (Box 1, Folder 3)